Bertie Charles Forbes Papers
Bertie Charles Forbes Papers
1892-1964
Forbes, B. C. (Bertie Charles), 1880-1954.
9.0 linear ft.
Papers of the American journalist, founder and editor of Forbes. Collection includes business and family correspondence (1897-1964); manuscript and/or published articles, biographical sketches, books and pamphlets, magazine and newspaper columns, novels, stories, speeches; and memorabilia, including clippings, photographs, and scrapbooks. Notable correspondents include Bruce Barton, Calvin Coolidge, Robert Dollar, George Eastman, Thomas Edison, Benjamin F. Fairless, James A. Farley, William Randolph Hearst, Herbert Hoover, Eddie Rickenbacker, John D. Rockefeller, Charles M. Schwab, Wendell Willkie, Owen D. Young, and others.
148984
Biographical History
Bertie Charles Forbes (1880-1954) was an American journalist and the founder and editor of Forbes magazine. He was born May 14, 1880 in New Deer, Aberdeenshire, Scotland to Robert and Agnes (Moir) Forbes. At the age of thirteen he taught himself shorthand and at fourteen began work as a printer's devil. In 1897 he began his journalistic career as a reporter for the Dundee Courier and during the next two years he progressed to sub-editor and editorial writer. At the same time he attended night school at University College in Dundee.
In 1901 Forbes left Scotland for South Africa, and he worked there as a reporter for various papers, including the Rand Daily Mail, which he also helped to establish. Three years later, he went to New York, where he found a position on the Journal of Commerce. By 1906 he was financial editor of that paper, as well as an editorial contributor to the Commercial and Financial Chronicle. He retained these positions until 1911 when he left to become the business and financial editor of the New York American. In 1916 he resigned that position in order to start his own business and financial magazine, Forbes, though he continued to write a syndicated column for the Hearst papers until 1942. The magazine was a success, reaching a circulation of 100,000 in the 1940s. It contained analyses of business trends and the economic situation of the country, as well as Forbes' personal style of business journalism. He pioneered the writing of personal profiles of business leaders and it was this for which he was most well-known.
In 1940-1941 Forbes served on the school board of Englewood, New Jersey, where he lived, creating controversy with charges that the social science textbooks used in the schools and one of the teachers were subversive. Beginning in 1942, he devoted his time to organizing Investor's League Inc., which protected and promoted the interests of stockholders and insurance policy-holders. He served as president of the group until 1949 and held the chairmanship of the board from 1949 until 1950, at which time he retired, after having attempted to resolve certain internal problems that had developed. During this period he began to withdraw from an active role in the publication of his magazine, turning over responsibility instead to his sons, Malcolm and Bruce.
Forbes married Adelaide Stevenson on April 20, 1915 and they had five sons: Bruce C., Malcolm S., Gordon B., Wallace F., and Duncan, who, as a young man, was killed in an automobile accident. Forbes died on May 6, 1954.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Bertie Charles Forbes Papers consist of correspondence, memorabilia, writings and miscellany.
Though Forbes was acquainted with many important men in business, finance, and government, and on intimate terms with some of them, very little or economic and political significance is found in the Correspondence, 1897-1964. The majority of the letters have no more than personal significance. Of particular interest, however, are a letter from F.D. Underwood, president of Erie Railroad, arguing that federal regulation of the railroads is necessary for their profitability; a letter from Bernard Baruch which discusses the experience of American business during W.W.I; a 1934 letter of Wendell Willkie discussing T.V.A.; 1942 letters from Herbert Hoover and Wendell Willkie politely refusing to head up Forbes' Investors League project; and letters from Roy Garvin, of the Afro-American newspapers, relating to Forbes' comments on the Detroit riots. Noteworthy also are xerox copies -- the original letters are not included in the collection -- of a series of 1923 letters between Herbert Hoover and Forbes with respect to Hoover's Toledo speech on war debts; and a 1920 series of correspondence between Forbes and Thomas A. Edison with respect to a story about Edison's bribing a sheriff to postpone a judgment. Of lesser significance are letters during 1931 which relate to a controversy over Sears, Roebuck's advertising of tires, and letters during 1940 which relate to Forbes' attempt, as a member of the Board of Education of Englewood, New Jersey, to ban as subversive the social science textbooks of Dr. Harold Rugg. Finally, the correspondence of the years 1930-1939 contains many letters from average American citizens expressing their experiences of the Depression, their analyses of the reasons for it, and their suggested solutions. The bulk of the correspondence for 1931 relates to Forbes' illness with pneumonia, and that for 1947 concerns the 30th anniversary of Forbes Magazine. There are short series of letters from Forbes to his sons Malcolm, 1942-1943, Gordon, 1943-1953, and Wallace, 1945-1953, and correspondence between Forbes and his friends and relatives in Scotland. The correspondence of 1954 through 1964 is made up essentially of letters to Forbes' sons, Malcolm and Bruce, regarding his death or containing reminiscences of his life.
Of significance are letters from the following with the inclusive dates of their correspondence:
Edward L. Doheny, 1924
Robert Dollar, 1922-1931
Thomas Alva Edison, 1920-1924
Benjamin Fairless, 1937-1953
Roy Garvin, 1944-1945
E.G. Grace, 1923-1952
Charles J. Hardy, 1943-1950
William Randolph Hearst, 1914-1915
Paul Hoffman, 1939-1953
William Holler, 1934-1955
Herbert Hoover, 1923-1953
Percy H. Johnston, 1919-1953
W. Alton Jones, 1934-1953
K.T. Keller, 1936-1950
Leroy A. Lincoln, 1939-1954
E.V. Rickenbacker, 1934-1952
John D. Rockefeller, Jr., 1939-1953
Charles M. Schwab, 1926-1938
F.D. Underwood, 1918
A. Vanderzee, 1940-1954
Thomas J. Warson, 1934-1952
Wendell Willkie, 1934-1942
Thomas E. Wilson, 1919-1952
Owen D. Young, 1922-1952
Of lesser research significance are letters from Bruce Barton, 1931-1946, Calvin Coolidge, 1929, George Eastman, 1916-1919, James A. Farley, 1939, Will H. Hayes, 1921-1940, Otto Kahn, 19141916, A.W. Mellon, 1929, Eugene Meyer, 1931-1934, Arthur Murray, 1938-1952, Robert A. Taft, 1949, Margaret Truman, 1950-1952, and John Wanamaker, 1917.
Memorabilia, 1892-1954, relate to various periods in Forbes' life in Scotland, South Africa and the United States. His early life in and continuing relationship to Scotland is represented by notebooks and copies of exams from his school days, statements by village officials recognizing his achievements and proficiency in shorthand, newspaper clippings detailing his visits to his old home and his generosity to the children who attended his old school, and letters of recommendation from newspapers for which he worked. An oversized scrapbook of clippings is filed at the end of the collection. His work as a reporter in South Africa is represented by some personal mementos, some notebooks, one of which includes observations apparently made on the trip to South Africa and another which contains impressions probably recorded on the extended trip he took in going from South Africa to the United States and letters of recommendation from the newspapers for which he worked. His life and work in the United States are represented by a large number of newspaper clippings which detail his travels, his speeches, and his views and opinions. A sizeable quantity of newspaper clippings which relate to the controversy on the Englewood Board of Education over the Rugg textbooks and an allegedly subversive teacher have been retained separately. Also found here are programs, invitations, advertisements and special issues of Forbes Magazine, publicity relating to awards Forbes gave and received and to special occasions, obituaries and other material relating to his death, two issues of magazines which relate to Forbes' career, and some scripts of radio appearances which he made. This United States material also includes seven scrapbooks: four containing newspaper clippings, one photographs (compiled after Forbes' death), one clippings of Forbes' obituaries, and one the cards Forbes received during the Christmas and New Year's season of 1953-1954. The latter two are oversized and have been placed at the end of the collection.
Writings, 189?-1953, include articles, books and pamphlets, magazine columns, newspaper columns, novels, short stories, and speeches. The dates of the materials are given when known. In addition, the magazine columns are grouped together according to the magazine in which they appeared and these groups are arranged alphabetically. In the case both of the magazine and newspaper columns, manuscript versions have been separated from and placed prior to the printed versions. The articles section contains both a scrapbook of a number of printed versions of an article Forbes wrote about California as it was published in various papers throughout the state and a copy of The American Dream, an anthology of articles, one of which was written by Forbes, that appeared in American Magazine. The books and pamphlets are all published versions. The newspaper columns do not constitute a complete run. The novel is an incomplete and unpublished typescript and appears to have been written prior to 1915. The short stories include both manuscript and printed versions of published and unpublished stories which Forbes wrote early in his career, none appearing to be later than 1920. The speeches contain both typescript and printed versions of the addresses given by Forbes. Included at the end of this material are four bound scrapbooks containing articles, sketches and interviews which span the years 1900-1910.
Miscellany, 1937, includes a typescript copy of John D. Rockefeller's memoirs, which were later published by Doubleday, and a typescript copy of a speech by George M. Verity on receiving Forbes' "Humanizer of Business" award.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged chronologically, with a folder of undated letters, arranged alphabetically by correspondent, at the beginning. Also included in the undated folder are a number of typewritten lists of correspondents and correspondence which seem to have been prepared by Forbes' secretary. Memorabilia is arranged with general biographical materials first, followed by materials relating to his life in Scotland, South Africa and the United States. Writings are arranged alphabetically by type and then by title, with the exception of newspaper columns, which are arranged chronologically. Untitled materials are arranged alphabetically by subject matter and placed at the end of their respective sections.
Subject and Genre Headings
Journalism; Barton, Bruce, 1886-1967.; Coolidge, Calvin, 1872-1933.; Dollar, Robert, 1844-1932.; Eastman, George, 1854-1932.; Edison, Thomas A. (Thomas Alva), 1847-1931.; Fairless, Benjamin F. (Benjamin Franklin), 1890-; Farley, James A. (James Aloysius), 1888-1976.; Forbes, B. C. (Bertie Charles), 1880-1954.; Hearst, William Randolph, 1863-1951.; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964.; Rickenbacker, Eddie, 1890-1973.; Rockefeller, John D., Jr. (John Davison), 1874-1960.; Schwab, Charles M., 1862-1939.; Willkie, Wendell L. (Wendell Lewis), 1892-1944.; Young, Owen D., 1874-1962.; Forbes.; Journalism -- United States.; Journalism, Commercial.; Journalists -- United States.; Newspapers -- Sections, columns, etc.; Periodical editors -- United States.; Scottish Americans.; Articles.; Books.; Correspondence.; Newspaper columns.; Pamphlets.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Speeches (documents); Editors.; Journalists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Forbes, Inc., 1964 and 1966.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Undated (Box 1)
  - 1897-1931, 19 folders (Box 1)
  - 1932-1946, 15 folders (Box 2)
  - 1947-1953, 9 folders (Box 3)
  - 1954-1964, 7 folders (Box 4)
- Memorabilia
  - General
    - Allan, Douglas, "B.C. Forbes", in Building Careers (Newark, N.J.: Lowden Publishers, 1934), 44-51 (Box 4)
    - Biographical sketches, holograph, typescript, typescript revised, typescript copy, typescript copy revised (Box 4)
    - "People, What They Are Doing: B.C. Forbes," Magazine World, II ( December 1945), 32, 34 (Box 4)
  - Scotland
    - Letters of recommendation, 1901; typescript copy (Box 5)
    - Notebooks
      - Agricultural notes, 1892?; holograph (Box 5)
      - English history notes, notes on salt, holograph (Box 5)
      - Literary clippings, printed material (Box 5)
      - Shorthand notes, 1892-1893; 1896; holograph; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Personal mementos (Box 5)
    - Scrapbook of events in Scotland, 1917-1954 (Oversize 1)
    - Trips to Scotland, printed material (Box 5)
  - South Africa
    - Letters of recommendation, 1904; typescript, typescript copy, (Box 5)
    - Notebooks
      - Literary notes, 1902; holograph (Box 5)
      - Travel notes, holograph (Box 5)
    - Personal mementos (includes Forbes' own list) (Box 5)
  - United States
    - Announcements of speeches (Box 6)
    - Board of Education, Englewood, New Jersey (Box 6)
    - Columns and editorials containing comment on Forbes Invitations (Box 6)
    - Obituary and posthumous tributes, 1954 (Box 6)
    - Personal mementos (Box 6)
    - Photographs and personal mementos (Vol. 1), 1935-1954 (Box 6)
    - Research report on readership of San Francisco Examiner financial writers, 1941 (Box 7)
    - Register of funeral home visitors, list of memorial contributions, New Jersey Assembly resolutions in memory of B.C. Forbes, New York State Saint Andrew's Society statement of sympathy, 1954 (Box 7)
    - Sales Executive Club of New York "Applause Award" to B.C. Forbes, miscellaneous publicity material, 1953 (Box 7)
    - Scrapbooks
      - Cards sent to Forbes during holiday season, 1953-1954 (Oversize 1)
      - Forbes obituaries, 1954 (Oversize 1)
    - Scripts of radio appearances, 1934; 1951 (Box 7)
    - Sears, Roebuck tire controversy, India Rubber and Tire Review, XXXI, 2, February 1931 (Box 7)
    - Surveys of newspaper column readership, lists of newspapers publishing Forbes' columns (Box 7)
    - Textbook controversy, Board of Education, Englewood, N.J., 1940-1941; printed material; 4 folders (Box 7)
    - 30th anniversary banquet, Forbes Magazine, 1947; programs, publicity, etc. (Box 7)
    - Trips and Speeches
      - Miscellaneous printed material, 1920-1953; undated; 4 folders (Box 7)
      - Scrapbook (Vol. 2), 1921-1934 (Box 8)
      - Scrapbook, Trip to West Coast (Vol. 3), 1925 (Box 8)
      - Scrapbook, Trips to California, Seattle, Texas (Vol. 4), 1928 (Box 8)
      - Scrapbook, Trip to Canada and Pacific Coast (Vol. 5), 1930 (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous
      - Advertisements containing Forbes' endorsements (Box 9)
      - Advertisements of books and newspaper columns (Box 9)
      - Forbes Magazine, early and special issues (Box 9)
      - Publicity material relating to Forbes Magazine Business Awards (Box 9)
      - Reports relating to business trips, 1934-1946 (Box 9)
- Writings
  - Articles
    - "American Banking's National Program," Banking, Feb 1936 (Box 9)
    - "Are you a Job-Holder or a Result-Getter," American Magazine, printed material annotated (Box 9)
    - "B.C. Forbes Tells How and Why Chains Fit Into Modern Scheme of Business," Chain Store Review, Apr 1928 (Box 9)
    - "Better Times Are Coming Now," Liberty Magazine, 1935 (Box 9)
    - "A Boy From the Ozarks: James L. Dalton", typescript copy revised (Box 9)
    - "Builds Success Stone Upon Stone", Forbes Magazine, Oct 14, 1919 (Box 9)
    - "Bulldozing by Wanamaker," Forbes Magazine, 1921 (Box 9)
    - "Business Improvement Forecast by Security Market", Forbes Magazine, May 13, 1922 (Box 9)
    - "Can You See Through Other Men's Eyes?" American Magazine, 1923; research material, typescript revised, typescript copy; draft A, typescript copy; draft B, typescript copy revised; printed material; 4 folders (Box 9)
    - "Charles M. Schwab: A Real Leader", Chicago Herald and Examiner, Apr 29, 1921 (Box 9)
    - "Courage Fathered Yellow Taxis; Service Made 'Em Grow," Forbes Magazine, 1924; draft, typescript copy; printed material; 2 folders (Box 9)
    - "The Criminal Railroads," Hearst's Magazine, Sep 1914; fragment (Box 9)
    - "Durant's Spectacular Effort to Stage Big Comeback," Forbes Magazine, Feb 15, 1925 (Box 9)
    - "Earns Public Goodwill As Well As Dividends," Forbes Magazine, Oct 14, 1922 (Box 9)
    - "Edison Working on How to Communicate With the Next World," American Magazine, printed material (Box 9)
    - "Edward R. Stettinius, Buyer of $3,000,000,000 War Supplies," Forbes Magazine, printed material (Box 9)
    - "The Etiquette of High Finance," Every Week, vol. 3, no. 20, Nov 13, 1916 (Box 9)
    - "Everybody Pays - you and you and you!" Cosmopolitan, 1935 (Box 9)
    - "A Faith that Removed Mountains," Earning Power, Apr 1917 (Box 9)
    - "Fifty Millionaires," McClure's Magazine, 1928 (Box 9)
    - "From Bank Clerk to Bank President," Forbes Magazine, Oct 5, 1918 (Box 9)
    - "'Gene' Grace - Whose Story Reads Like a Fairy Tale," American Magazine, Jul 1920 (Box 9)
    - "A Genius Who Never Walked A Step," American Magazine, Apr 1920 (Box 9)
    - "Getting Big Men to Talk," Frank Woolworth, Forbes Magazine, 1917 (Box 9)
    - "Getting Big Men to Talk," George Eastman, Forbes Magazine, 1917 (Box 9)
    - "Giannini: The Story of an Unusual Career," Forbes Magazine, Nov 10, 1923 (Box 9)
    - "Give Me The West!" American Magazine, May 1920; printed material revised (Box 9)
    - "The Grand Old Man of the Pacific," Service Magazine, typescript copy (Box 9)
    - "He Built Success From Failures," Hearst's Magazine, Apr 1921; fragment (Box 9)
    - "He Heads Two Gigantic Enterprises," Forbes Magazine, 1919 (Box 9)
    - "He Recognizes His Men," Hearst's Magazine, 1918? (Box 9)
    - "Heads Billion - Dollar Corporation at 39 - Recipe For Success," Forbes Magazine, Jun 15, 1930; draft, typescript copy revised; printed material; 2 folders (Box 9)
    - "Here is Good Cheer," Independence, Sep 1922 (Box 9)
    - "His Novel Rules for Reaching Top," Forbes Magazine, 1920 (Box 10)
    - "Hoover Tells How to Preserve American Living Standards," (an interview), Forbes Magazine, Apr 29, 1922 (Box 10)
    - "How American Red Cross Is Binding Europe's Wounds," Forbes Magazine, Jan 15, 1918 (Box 10)
    - "How Big Businessman Grew Rich: V. George Eastman," Hearst's Magazine, Feb 1920 (Box 10)
    - "How Big Businessman Grew Rich: VIII. Percy H. Johnston," Hearst's Magazine, Nov 1920 (Box 10)
    - "How Big Men Grew Rich: XVI. James S. Alexander," Hearst's Magazine, 1921? (Box 10)
    - "How Big Businessman Grew Rich: James A. Alexander," Hearst's Magazine, 1921?; typescript copy (Box 10)
    - "How 20 Million People Drove Wall St. Wild," McClure's Magazine, 1928 (Box 10)
    - "How Forbes Gets Big Men to Talk," Forbes Magazine, Sep 15, 1917 (Box 10)
    - "How Is This For Rapid Climbing?" Forbes Magazine, Jan 24, 1920 (Box 10)
    - "How Paul Shoup Made His Mark," Forbes Magazine, Oct 13, 1923 (Box 10)
    - "I Tried to be a Quitter," Forbes Magazine, Jun 1, 1946 (Box 10)
    - "Initiative Keynote of His Success," Forbes Magazine, 1919 (Box 10)
    - "Introducing the New Head of Our Biggest Bank," Forbes Magazine, Jan 15, 1933 (Box 10)
    - "John L. Lewis: A Short Review of His Life", 1937; typescript copy revised, (Box 10)
    - "Labor To Become Capital! Owen D. Young's Vision," Forbes Magazine, 1927 (Box 10)
    - "Let Well Enough Alone", 1922; printed material (Box 10)
    - "The Man Who Puts Investments Through the 'Third Degree,'" Forbes Magazine, Oct 1, 1924 (Box 10)
    - "Master at Handling Railway Men," Forbes Magazine, 1920; draft, typescript revised; draft fragment, typescript revised; printed material (Box 10)
    - "Men Who Are Making America" series in Leslie's Illustrated Weekly Newspaper
      - Dr. Alexander Graham Bell, Apr 19, 1917 (Box 10)
      - Albert J. Earling, Oct 6, 1917 (Box 10)
      - Thomas A. Edison, May 24, 1917 (Box 10)
      - Henry Ford, Apr 26, 1917 (Box 10)
      - John Hays Hammond, Feb 22, 1917 (Box 10)
      - Cyrus H. McCormick, May 31, 1917 (Box 10)
      - John Pierpont Morgan, Apr 5, 1917 (Box 10)
      - John D. Ryan, May 10, 1917 (Box 10)
      - John G. Shedd, Mar 8, 1917 (Box 10)
      - Cornelius Vanderbilt, III, Apr 19, 1917 (Box 10)
      - Frank W. Woolworth, Mar 15, 1917 (Box 10)
    - "My Adventures In Self-Reliance," American Magazine, 1920 (Box 10)
    - "New Business Star: Harriman the Second," Forbes Magazine, Oct 30, 1920 (Box 10)
    - $1,250 For A Shine," American Magazine, Mar 1922; draft; typescript copy revised; printed material (Box 10)
    - "Our Termite Taxes," Hearst's International Cosmopolitan -, Oct 1936 (Box 10)
    - "Owen D. Young: A Revolutionary Capitalist," McClure's Magazine, draft, typescript revised; printed material (Box 10)
    - "To Reach the Top Be the Best Man at the Bottom," Hearst's Magazine, printed material (Box 10)
    - "Review of 1913 and Outlook for 1914," Business and Finance, reprinted from New York American (Box 10)
    - "The Rise of Percy H. Johnston," Personal Efficiency, Jan 1920 (Box 10)
    - "Robert Dollar: Founder, Dollar Steamship Lines," Forbes Magazine, 1923; typescript revised, printed material revised (Box 10)
    - "A Romance of the Rubber Industry," Forbes Magazine, Jun 26, 1920 (Box 10)
    - "Savings: the Motive Power of Industry," Independence, Jun 1922 (Box 10)
    - "Scotch Spendthrifts," McClure's Magazine, 1929; draft, typescript copy revised printed material (Box 10)
    - "Seven Master Keys to Successful Selling," Salesman's Digest, vol. 1, no. 1, 1953 (Box 10)
    - "The Smithy" (unpublished and incomplete), 189?; holograph notes, (Box 10)
    - "Stirring Adventures, Then Fortune," Forbes Magazine, printed material revised (Box 10)
    - "They All Knew He Would Reach the Top," Forbes Magazine, Jan 15, 1940 (Box 10)
    - "Tips to Young Money Managers," College Humor, 1932?; 1933?; draft; typescript copy; printed material (Box 10)
    - "Toil, Smile and Listen!" Hearst's Magazine, 1918 (Box 10)
    - "Was Duke, Tobacco King, A Success or a Failure," Forbes Magazine, typescript copy revised (Box 10)
    - "Ways to Win in 1932" Premier Rayon Review, Apr 1932 (Box 10)
    - "'We Face the Future Without Fear, With Faith' - Sloan," Forbes Magazine, March 29, 1924 (Box 10)
    - "'We Must Improve It,' Is Bassett's Motto," Forbes Magazine, Nov 1, 1924; draft, typescript copy revised; printed material (Box 10)
    - "What Big Men Tell Me About Success," Every Week, Apr 2, 1917 (Box 10)
    - "What Chance Has the Office Boy?" Every Week, IV, 2, Jan 8, 1917 (Box 10)
    - "What the Oil Industry Must Do," Forbes Magazine, Jun 1, 1930 (Box 10)
    - "Why Knock the Supreme Court, Mister Editor?" The American Press, Feb 1936 (Box 10)
    - "Why Woolworth's Has Succeeded," Forbes Magazine, 1919 (Box 10)
    - "Will America Ever See Real Prosperity Again?" Cosmopolitan, 1935 (Box 10)
    - "The Women of Wall Street," Every Week, vol. 4, no. 9, Feb 26, 1917 (Box 10)